Guide to the Howland - Mcintosh Family Papers, 1713-1997 (bulk 1830-1989) RL.00578
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Howland-Mcintosh Family papers
1713-1997 (bulk 1830-1989)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Howland-McIntosh family
RL.00578
6.3 Linear Feet
Families originally from Carteret and Moore Counties, N.C. Correspondence; legal files, including deeds and wills; photographs; many genealogical materials; financial papers; postcards; paper currency; two scrapbooks; and school papers, all relating to the Howland and the McIntosh families from Carteret, Durham, and Moore Counties, N.C. Photographs include tintypes, albumen prints, and one daguerrotype. Many legal files pertain to a lengthy court case involving the transfer of family property on Shackleford Banks, N.C. to the federal government. Oversize materials include aerial photographs and land surveys of Shackleford Banks and other family properties, and photostats of early deeds. Though several photographs and all the currency date from the Civil War, the only other original documentation on the families' Civil War activities is a signed oath of allegiance to the Union dated 1865, and a few letters referring at length to the circumstances surrounding the confiscation of one Howland's property in Beaufort, N.C. during the war, and his attempts at legal restitution. William F. Howland (1876-1951) married Mary Elizabeth McIntosh (1878-1964) in 1903. The collection contains much of their correspondence. Other correspondence includes World War I letters from a McIntosh son, Leland Carson. The addition (04-129)(25 items, 1.5 lin. ft.; dated [1870s]-[1960s]) consists primarily of materials, including a scrapbook, photo album, letters, and travel journals, kept by Mary Howland Dawson from the 1950 "Youth Caravan to Germany" sponsored by the Methodist Conference of North Carolina. Also includes two family photograph albums, with images dating back to the 1870s; clippings about various family members; and an historical sketch of Salem United Methodist Church in Garland, N.C. This addition is unprocessed and is not represented in the finding aid.
2,147 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Howland - McIntosh Family Papers were donated to Duke University in 1997.
Collection Overview
The Howland-McIntosh Family Papers span the years 1713-1997, with the bulk of the papers being dated from 1830-1989. They chronicle the personal lives and business affairs of three North Carolina families: the Howlands, the McIntoshes, and, to a much lesser extent, the Dawsons. The Howlands settled in Carteret County in the early eighteenth century, buying properties in and near Beaufort and on the Shackleford Banks. Their occupations included sea captains, millers, carpenters, small farmers, and insurance agents. Howland descendants married members of the McIntosh family, who were then living in Moore County. Eventually, descendants of these families moved briefly into Durham County in the late 19th/early 20th centuries. The Dawson family represented in this collection is related by marriage to the Howland-McIntosh family, and a descendant still lives in Durham County. The collection is rich in documents relating to the history of Carteret County, N.C. from the early 18th to the late 20th centuries, especially relating to the Outer Banks, including Shackleford Banks, now part of the Cape Lookout National Seashore. Eighteenth and nineteenth century legal papers in the collection chiefly document early land ownership, and there are also many family wills.
The collection consists of correspondence, legal papers, financial papers, photographs -- including daguerreotypes, tintypes, and albumen prints, printed materials such as periodicals and posters, school records and compositions, scrapbooks, postcards, stereograph cards, and a few artifacts. The bulk of the collection is made up of correspondence and many legal papers, especially deeds and indentures. There is little material directly concerning the Civil War in this collection; however, information on the families' activities during this period can be found in 20th century sources in the genealogical materials folders.
Family relationships and daily personal matters are documented in the Correspondence Series, which includes a long series of love letters written from 1903-1904 between William F. Howland II and Mary McIntosh Howland. Another series of letters originated from Leland C. McIntosh during his military service in World War I, chiefly in France and Belgium. These mainly concern routine family matters, but give some insight into camp life and the effect of the war on the soldiers. Leland also sent home souvenirs of his stay, including a 1914 Iron Cross which is housed in the Artifacts Series, along with a 1893 pin from Grover Cleveland's presidential inauguration. Other principal correspondents include William F. Howland, Sr., Ralph Howland, and Emma J. Howland; the remaining correspondents include several other family members and friends. Other family correspondence is located in the Scrapbooks Series and the Shackleford Banks (N.C.) Legal Papers Series.
Documents pertaining to specific members of these families and their financial and legal activities, particularly land ownership and household expenses, can be found in two family series. The Howland Family Series contains folders for papers grouped by various family members: Ralph Howland (1793-1866) and his wife Eliza Bell Howland (1810-1883); Zephaniah Howland (1752-1834?); Levi C. Howland (1834-?); and Emma J. Howland (1851-1920). Contents include deeds, mortgages, indentures, bills, receipts, estate papers, and a few recipes for home remedies. The Zephaniah Howland folder contains three petitions (1832-33) relating to his request for a military pension based on his participation in the Revolutionary War; these documents contain numerous details of his service. The Levi C. Howland folder contains an oath of allegiance to the Union signed by William F. Howland in 1865. Another mention of the impact of the Civil War on the Howlands is a document in the Ralph Howland legal papers which records his petition in 1866 to have confiscated property in Beaufort town restored to his rightful ownership. Also in this series is genealogical information on the Howland family, who descended from Henry Howland, brother of John Howland, original Mayflower passenger. The McIntosh Family Series contains legal papers (chiefly deeds); McIntosh children's school records, including many compositions; numerous clippings; obituaries; a few wills; and other information on family members.
Further information on the Howland, McIntosh, and Dawson families can be obtained from the two albums in the Scrapbooks Series. A McIntosh album chiefly records through the medium of commercial postcards Leland McIntosh's travels in Europe during the period 1917-1919. Some offer scenes of military camp life in Camp Greenleaf, Ga., and in France; others display routine views of Belgium, and the Italian and French rivieras. There are also some greeting cards, chiefly from the 1920s. The second album belonged to the Howland family and conveys many insights into the family's lives during the 20th century. Several descendants were alumni of Duke University; their academic and social activities there are documented through clippings, commencement booklets, and other Items. Other materials mounted in this album include many pieces of correspondence, photographs, postcards, war ration booklets, and greeting cards. Many postcards in both of these albums present views of 19th and 20th-century N.C. coastal areas. Other postcards can also be found in the Postcards Series.
The Shackleford Banks (N.C.) Series concerns a lengthy legal process transferring ownership of the Howland property on Shackleford Banks, N.C. to the federal government. The series is divided into two subseries: the Legal Papers Subseries contains all legal files from the attorney's offices, while the much smaller Family Papers Subseries originated from the family's own personal files. The litigation began in 1959 and ended in 1985 with the inclusion of the Shackleford Banks in the Cape Lookout National Seashore, and is richly documented in this collection through attorney-client and family correspondence, many deeds, land surveys and appraisals, court records, genealogical records, other legal and financial papers, and clippings. Researchers interested in the history of the Outer Banks of N.C. will be interested to find many photostats and photocopies of early Carteret County deeds and other legal papers, including a Lords Proprietor land grant to John Porter dated 1713. Many of these Items have been stored in the oversize materials section.
The Photographs and Artifacts Series provides portraits of family members from circa 1860 to the mid-20th century, including some in Confederate uniform. Most of the individuals, however, are unidentified. Also included in this series are a small group of early twentieth century stereograph cards, and a few artifacts.
Howland-McIntosh family
- Correspondence Series, 1874-1924and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Letters written between family members and a few friends. Chief correspondents are William F. Howland I (1844-1896);Ralph Howland (1848-1906);William F. Howland II (1876-1951);his wife, Mary Elizabeth McIntosh Howland (1878-1964);Betty Warren Howland King (1881?-1930); and Leland Carson McIntosh (1873-1932).Topics generally cover courtship, family relationships, health, and daily activities. The largest series of letters was written by William F. Howland to Mary McIntosh Howland during their courtship and after their wedding while he was living and working in Durham, N.C., and she was in Carthage (Moore County), N.C. One smaller series of letters from Leland C. McIntosh originated from U.S. military training camps and from overseas during the last few years of World War I, and offers some details about camp life and hardships on the front. Letters are arranged chronologically.
  - Letters to and from William F. Howland I (1844-1896), 1874, Oct. 25-1896, June 18 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Ralph Howland (1848-1906), 1875, Oct. 23-1875, Nov. 3and undated (Box 1)
  - William F. Howland II to Mary McIntosh Howland, 5 folders
    - 1903, July 6-1903, July 19 (Box 1)
    - 1903, July 20-1903, Aug.7 (Box 1)
    - 1903, Aug. 9-1903, Dec. 29 (Box 1)
    - 1903, Dec. 30-1904, May 30 (Box 1)
    - 1904, July 24-1905, Jan. 17and undated (Box 1)
  - Mary McIntosh Howland to William F. Howland II, 2 folders
    - 1903, June 2-1903, Aug. 11 (Box 1)
    - 1903, Aug. 11-1909, Feb. 9and undated (Box 1)
  - Letters to Mary McIntosh Howland, 1902, May 12-1943, Jan. 26and undated (Box 1)
  - Betty Warren Howland King to William F. Howland II, other Howland family members, and miscellaneous correspondence, 1915-1934and undated (Box 1)
  - Letters to [T.C.?] Lindsay, 1835, Nov.3; 1836?; 1844, May 22 (Box 1)
  - Letters to and From William F. Howland II and Mary McIntosh Howland, and various Howland family letters 1890, Oct. 2-[192-?] and undated (Box 1)
  - William F. Howland II to Ralph Howland, 1902, Aug. 1-1905, Feb. 22and undated (Box 1)
  - Leland C. McIntosh to Elizabeth Howland; 1919, June 13 (contains fabric souvenirs) (Box 1)
  - Letter to Eliza Bell Howland from Aunt S. J. Howard, 1860, June 29 (Box 1)
  - Letters to and from Emma J. Howland; 1907, Jan. 1-1920, Mar. 22and undated (Box 2)
  - Leland Carson McIntosh to Mr. and Mrs. William F. Howland II and other family members and friends; 1917, Oct. 11-1924, July7 (Box 2)
- Howland Family Series, 1736-1988and undated
  Documents -- chiefly legal and financial papers -- pertaining to the Howland family of Carteret County, N.C. Genealogical materials include photocopies from 20th century genealogical sources, genealogical charts, photocopied information on the family's Civil War activities, and some correspondence between modern descendants. Arranged by individual family members or groups of closely related family members; within folders, arranged in chronological order.
  - Genealogical Materials, 1789-1988and undated (Box 2)
  - Ralph Howland (1793-1866): Deeds and other Legal Papers, 1736-1866and undated (Box 2)
  - Ralph Howland (1793-1866): Financial Papers, 1826-1865and undated (Box 2)
  - Ralph Howland (1793-1866): Domestic Accounts, 1847 (Box 2)
  - Eliza Bell Howland (1810-1883): Legal and Financial Papers, 1830-1872 (Box 2)
  - Zephaniah Howland [ca. 1752-1834]: Legal and Financial Papers, 1832, Sept. 18-1835, Apr. 10; 1914, July 8 (Box 2)
  - Levi C. Howland (1834-?), et al.: Legal and Financial Papers, 1865-1921and undated (Box 2)
  - Emma J. Howland (1851-1920): Financial and Legal Papers, 1895-[1926] and undated (Box 2)
  - Levi C. Howland (1834-?), Zephaniah J. Howland (1842-1903), and Ralph Howland (1848-1906): Miscellaneous Bills and Receipts, 1830-1886and undated (Box 2)
- McIntosh Family Series, 1803-1927and undated
  Documents pertaining to the McIntosh family of Moore County, N.C. which relate to land ownership, family genealogy, and the school activities of three McIntosh children. The genealogical information derives chiefly from materials related to deaths in the family, including clippings, obituaries, memorial booklets, copies of wills, estate settlement papers, and funeral expenses. The school papers contain large numbers of compositions, some of which contain descriptions of regional life and social conditions. Documents are arranged chronologically by year with the exception of the school papers, which are grouped under the individual names of the children.
  - McIntosh and Sowell Family Deeds, 1803-1906 (Moore County) (Box 2)
  - McIntosh Family Deaths, 1829-1927:
    - Garrett Parker (d. 1829), A. S. McIntosh (d. 1915), Patience Clementine Parker McIntosh (d. 1927), and information about other family members (Box 2)
  - Mollie McIntosh, Mary E. McIntosh, and Leland Carson McIntosh -- School Papers, 1895-1896and undated (Box 2)
- Postcards Series, ca. 1950s-1973 and undated
  The majority of these postcards are undated. Most feature views of N.C. coastal areas, especially Beaufort, Shackleford Banks, Portsmouth Island, Cape Lookout, and Fort Macon. Some also contain 19th and early 20th century views of Beaufort taken from prints and photographs.
  - 1950s-1973 and undated, 1 folder (Box 2)
- Shackleford Banks (N.C.) Series, 1713-1987and undated (bulk 1978-1987)
  The largest series in the collection documents the lengthy and complicated legal proceedings, beginning in the 1960sand ending in 1989,which transferred land on Shackleford Banks, N.C., from private owners to the federal government for inclusion in the Cape Lookout National Seashore. The series is divided into two subseries as found in the original collection, Legal Papers and Family Papers, both of which consist mainly of attorney-client correspondence, court documents, and many pieces of documentary evidence used in the case, such as land surveys and deeds.
  There are many photocopies of original documents from the 18th and 19th centuries, chiefly deeds documenting land ownership on the Shackleford Banks, Carteret County. The earliest of these is a photostat of a land grant from the Lords Proprietors to John Porter, 1713. Materials are not arranged chronologically, but were kept in the original order imposed on them by the attorneys' offices and the Howland family. Many items in this series are found in the oversize section of the collection. All folder titles were taken from the file labels created by the attorneys' offices and the Howland family. Annotations from attorney's folders are also noted on the front of the file folders.
  - Legal Papers Subseries, 1713-1987and undated
    - Legal Papers "from Ralph Howland folder," 1828-1832 (Box 3)
    - Legal and Financial Papers (chiefly tax receipts), 1890-1933 (Box 3)
    - Legal Papers (chiefly deeds), "from Levi C. Howland folder," 1868-1918 (Box 3)
    - Shackleford Banks; General Abstract Appeals, 85 Civ 1073:
      - Genealogy, Court Documents, Title Records, 1818-1987, undated (Box 3)
      - Genealogy, Court Documents, Title Records, 1829-1982, undated (Box 3)
      - Beveridge File; Genealogy, Court Documents, Title Records, 1853-1978, undated (Box 3)
      - Copies of Attorney-Client Contract and Complete Copies of Special Master Proceedings attached to motion for Summary Judgment # 1941, 1976-1985 (Box 3)
      - Title Searches, Client-Attorney Correspondence, 1967-1979 (Box 3)
      - Fees for Shackleford Banks Appraisals, ca. 1980s (Box 3)
      - Title Searches, 1713-1979, undated (Box 3)
      - Court Documents, Correspondence:
        - 1912-1979 (Box 3)
        - 1963, 1979 (Box 3)
        - 1978-1985 (Box 3)
    - Shackleford Banks, General Abstract Appeals, 85 Civ 1073: (cont'd) (Box 4)
      - Court Documents and Correspondence, 1963-1980and undated (Box 4)
      - Carteret Superior Court; Court Documents and Correspondence, 1895-1982and undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Court Documents and Correspondence:
        - 1978-1985and undated (Box 4)
        - 1982-1985and undated (Box 4)
        - 1982-1985and undated (Box 4)
        - 1962-1983, undated (Box 4)
      - Court Documents and Correspondence (Howland Correspondence file #1941) 1960-1978, 1980-1984 (Box 4)
      - Court Documents and Correspondence, undated (Box 4)
      - Transcript of Beveridge, et al. vs. Howland, et al., Carteret County, no. 79, CvS 453, Certified 1980, Mar.6 (Box 4)
    - Shackleford Banks, General Abstract Appeals, 85 Civ 1073 (cont'd.) (Box 5)
      - Court Documents, Correspondence:
        - 1978-1980 (Box 5)
        - 1980-1984 (Box 5)
      - Record and Statement of Case on Appeal; Geraldine Beveridge et al. vs. William F. Howland, III, et al.:
        - 1831-1899, 1979 (Box 5)
        - 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Family Papers Subseries, 1963-1985and undated
    - Shackleford Banks Folder--Correspondence, Tax Receipts, Copies of Court Documents, etc., 1932-1978 (Box 5)
    - Shackleford Banks Folder--Correspondence, Tax Receipts, Copies of Court documents, etc., 1978-1980 (Box 5)
    - Shackleford Banks File--Correspondence, Tax Receipts, Copies of Court Documents, etc., 1963-1985 (Box 5)
    - Shackleford--Recent File: Correspondence, Tax estimates and statements, Attorney fees, Final settlement, and miscellaneous papers, 1982-1985, undated (Box 5)
    - Shackleford--Recent File: Correspondence, Tax estimates and statements, Attorney fees, Final settlement, and miscellaneous papers, 1982-1985, undated (Box 5)
- Scrapbooks Series, 1860s-1997 and undated
  Two scrapbooks belonging to the McIntosh and Howland families. They contain many varieties of memorabilia, including: correspondence; postcards; greeting cards, including some Valentines; clippings; photographs; stock certificates; receipts; rail passes; commencement programs and other school mementos; World War II ration books; and the will of Mary McIntosh Howland. A series of postcards from World War I was sent by Leland C. McIntosh to his family, and depict scenes of camp life and portraits of notable military leaders; many more are from the years just after World War I, and show views of France, Belgium, the French Riviera, and Italy. Other postcards from the early 20th century show views of Beaufort and Henderson, N.C. Items in scrapbooks are arranged in rough chronological order by year.
  - McIntosh Family Scrapbook, ca. 1910-1926and undated (Box 6)
  - Howland Family Scrapbook, 1860s-1997 and undated (Box 7)
- Photographs and Artifacts Series, [ ca. 1862]-1913 and undated
  Chiefly cased tintypes, but also one cased daguerreotype and a few loose tintypes. Identifications are quoted from donor's labels. A collection of stereograph cards includes artistic scenes from the life of Jesus Christ, and various photographs of landscapes from the United States and abroad. The Iron Cross was sent by Leland C. McIntosh to his family from France.
  - 1 cased tintype: "Levi C. Howland, ca. 1862" (Box 8)
  - 1 cased tintype: "Asa Seawell McIntosh, 1842-1915in Confederate uniform, undated (Box 8)
  - 1 cased tintype, no cover: unidentified man in Confederate uniform, undated (Box 8)
  - 1 cased tintype: " [? ] Parker, father of Patience Clementine Parker, m. Asa McIntosh," undated (Box 8)
  - 1 cased tintype, undated (Box 8)
  - 2 uncased tintypes, undated (Box 8)
  - 1 cased daguerreotype, undated (Box 8)
  - 1 cased tintype: "Levi C. Howland," undated (Box 8)
  - Cased tintype, inlaid with abalone: unidentified man, possibly in Confederate naval uniform, undated (Box 8)
  - Inaugural Pin, U.S. Presidency, 1893 (Box 8)
  - Iron Cross, 1913 (Box 8)
  - Stereographs [ ca. 1910] (Box 8)
- Oversize Materials
  - Howland Family Series
    - Deed, Carteret County, N.C., 1794, July 9 (Box 9)
    - Levi C. Howland (1834-?), et al.; Legal and Financial Papers:
      - Obituary for Mrs. S. Bell, 1868, Dec. 25 (Box 9)
      - Deed, E. H. Howland to Zephaniah J. Howland and W. F. Howland, 1885, Dec.3 (Box 9)
      - Mortgage Deed, Mary J. Pigott to Sarah A. Davis, 1888, Feb. 27 (Box 9)
      - Mortgage Deed, Emma J. Howland to Thomas Thomas, 1891, Jan.5 (Box 9)
      - Mortgage Deed with Insurance Clause, Emma J. Howland to Bank of Beaufort, 1906, Dec.5 (Box 9)
      - Mortgage Deed with Insurance Clause, W. F. Howland II and Wife to Bank of Beaufort, 1907, Apr.9 (Box 9)
      - Copies of Deeds, 1884, July3; 1889, March6; 1867, Dec. 24; 1841, Feb.4 (Box 9)
      - 1910, Jan. 4Mortgage Deed with Insurance Clause: Emma J. Howland to Dr. George Davis (Box 9)
    - Ralph Howland (1793-1866), Land Survey, undated (Box 9)
    - By-Laws of the Farmers' Sub-Alliance at North River, undated (Box 9)
  - McIntosh Family Series
    - McIntosh and Sowell Deeds, 1803-1906;Warranty Deed: W. Jackson and wife to A. S. McIntosh, 1906, May 8 (Box 9)
    - McIntosh and Sowell Deeds, 1803-1906;Deed: J. B. Kelly to A. Sowell, 1840, May (Box 9)
  - Photographs and Artifacts Series
    - [Charles?] McIntosh, [ca. 192-?] (Box 9)
    - Unidentified woman, [ca. 18-?] (Box 9)
    - Clem McIntosh, [ca. 192-?] (Box 9)
    - Thomas McIntosh and unidentified woman, albumen print, [19-?] (Box 9)
    - Leland C. McIntosh, albumen print, [ 1918?] (Box 9)
    - WWI photo, France [ 1917?] (Box 9)
    - Large tintype, undated[Parker?] (Box 9)
  - Shackleford Banks (N.C.) Series
    - Legal Papers Subseries
      - Shackleford Banks, General Abstract Appeals, 85 Civ 1073: Photostat of Land Grant from Lords Proprietors to John Porter, 1713, Nov. 10 (Box 9)
      - Shackleford Banks, General Abstract Appeals, 85 Civ 1073:
        - (Illegible), undated (Box 9)
        - Photostat of Deed: Enoch Ward, James Shackleford, John Shackleford to [?Thompson] and Martha, his wife, [17??] (Box 9)
      - Shackleford Banks, General Abstract Appeals, 85 Civ 1073:
        - Carteret/Superior Court, Photostat of Howland Family Tree, undated (Box 9)
        - Copy [very faded] of Document Establishing lines and Boundaries: Agreement Between William P. Marshall and Ralph Howland, 1859, Feb. 21 (Box 9)
        - Photocopy of Record of Administrators, Executors, Guardians: Orphie Lindsay Howland, deceased; W. F. Howland, administrator; 1909, Jan. 12 (Box 9)
        - Photocopy of Title: John Porter to Col. William Brice, 1715, May 10 (Box 9)